"The Risks and Benefits
of Chondroitin for Osteoarthritis"
Chondroitin is a structural
component of cartilage
commonly used
as a dietary supplement
for osteoarthritis
that shares a similar story
with glucosamine.
There's a large heterogeneity
in outcomes,
with the industry-funded studies
showing a benefit
for symptomatic relief
and the non-industry-funded
studies showing no effect,
with a small effect size
similar to glucosamine.
Considering just the largest,
best-run studies,
the benefit of chondroitin
was found to be
"minimal or nonexistent"
and its use "therefore
be discouraged."
Like glucosamine,
the current American College
of Rheumatology guidelines
"strongly recommend against"
the use of as chondroitin
for knee or hip osteoarthritis,
along with the American Academy
of Orthopedic Surgeons
and Osteoarthritis Research
Society International,
whereas the European Society
for Clinical
and Economic Aspects
of Osteoporosis,
Osteoarthritis,
and Musculoskeletal Diseases
again allow
for the use
of pharmaceutical-grade,
prescription-only chondroitin.
Chondroitin is
typically extracted
from animal cartilage-
shark fins, bovine,
and chicken windpipes,
or pig noses-
and slaughterhouse
supply chains
are not known for their "good
manufacturing practices."
The lack of purity
and presence of contaminants
is blamed in part for the lack
of consistent reproducibility.
A study of 32 chondroitin
supplements on the market
found that only five
contained the labeled amount,
and some contained none.
Terms like "quality tested"
or retail price
were found to provide no basis
for judging quality.
Some of the cheapest
and the most expensive
chondroitin on the market
contained less than 10 percent
actual chondroitin.
When the National
Institutes of Health
set out to design
the esteemed GAIT trial,
the Glucosamine/Chondroitin
Arthritis Intervention Trial,
they ruled out
20 different commercial products
for issues like quality control
before giving up
and just deciding to have it
specially made themselves.
More than 1500 patients
with symptomatic
knee osteoarthritis
were randomized to take
standard daily doses
of glucosamine, chondroitin,
both glucosamine
and chondroitin,
an NSAID
anti-inflammatory drug,
or a placebo for six months.
Only the drug beat out placebo
for pain management.
Neither glucosamine
and chondroitin alone
or in combination
reduced pain effectively,
and neither did it have
any significant effect
on delaying disease progression
on X-ray.
Chondroitin also failed
in a two-year study,
but two other trials
found that by year two
objective benefits
could be found,
and a third using
more sensitive imaging (MRI)
could pick up
protective effects
by six months.
If you want to give it a try,
there's now
a purified non-animal source
of chondroitin
made from scratch
that should be free
of contaminants.
In the U.S., chondroitin
and glucosamine
are almost always sold
in a combination pill.
Like in the GAIT trial,
a meta-analysis of studies
pitting both
against osteoarthritis
found no clinically significant
benefit.
However, there had
never been a trial
in which pharmaceutical-grade,
prescription-only preparations
of both were used together
until finally
one was published in 2017.
The multicenter
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled
clinical trial
had to be stopped prematurely
because one group was doing
so much better than the other
that it was deemed unethical
to continue.
See how much more
one of the treatments
was reducing pain?
But that superior treatment
was the placebo!
Unexpectedly,
when the code was broken,
it turned out that
the placebo group did better!
In other words,
the industry-funded study
found that their own
pharmaceutical-grade
chondroitin/glucosamine
was making the pain
significantly worse
compared to a sugar pill.
In the sugar pill group,
47 percent had
at least a 50 percent
improvement
in pain or function,
compared to just 28 percent
in the chondroitin/glucosamine
group.
What the chondroitin/glucosamine
users did get
was more side effects,
such as diarrhea
and abdominal pain;
so, doctors may want
to tell their patients
to stop taking their glucosamine
and chondroitin
as it is less effective
than placebo.